<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The apology of Theophilus Higgons lately minister, now Catholique VVherein the letter of Sir Edvv. Hoby Knight, directed vnto the sayd T.H. in answere of his first motiue, is modestly examined, and clearely refuted.</title>
            <author>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850169</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850169</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1488:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The apology of Theophilus Higgons lately minister, now Catholique VVherein the letter of Sir Edvv. Hoby Knight, directed vnto the sayd T.H. in answere of his first motiue, is modestly examined, and clearely refuted.</title>
                  <author>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Machvel, dwelling in the streete of the prison, ouer against the Crowne of Orlea[n]s,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Roan :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Theophilus Higgons.</note>
                  <note>Errata sheet on the verso of page 55 bears the statement: Errours passed in some copies.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; some pages cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hoby, Edward, --  Sir, 1560-1617.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE APOLOGY OF THEOPHILVS HIGGONS LATELY MINISTER, NOW CATHOLIQVE.</p>
            <p>VVherein THE LETTER OF SIR EDVV. HOBY KNIGHT, directed vnto the ſayd T. H. in anſwere of his FIRST MOTIVE, is modeſtly examined, and clearely refuted. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Patior, ſed non confundor.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Timoth. 1.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>ROAN.</p>
            <p>By IOHN MACHVEL, dwelling in the ſtreete of the Priſon, ouer againſt the Crowne of Orlea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND TRVLY VERTVOVS, the LADIES CATHOLIQVE of great Britany.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Illustrious, and Renovvned Ladies;</p>
            <p>It vvas the opinion of an ancient, and graue <note n="a" place="margin">Thucydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian, that <hi>men ſhould ſpeake nothing of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; neither good, nor euill.</hi> An opinion vnvvorthy of the Authour; vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch as <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>In his Treatiſe</hi> of the vertuous acts of vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> approoueth not in his cenſure, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sir <hi>Edward Hoby,</hi> nor my ſelf, haue obſerued in our practiſe; hovvbeit, in a different manner, and vpon vnlike respects: he speaking <hi>euill</hi> of you, to the diſparadgement of your <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ites; I <hi>good,</hi> to the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cement of your honours: he, out of his Zeale, and VViſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (vvhich, perhappes, did both ſet forth together, as <note n="c" place="margin">Curreba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſimul, ſed ille praecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit. <hi>Io.</hi> 20.4.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> but yet the firſt hath outrunne the ſecond) he, I ſay, out of his zeale, and vviſedome, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame your Religion in your Perſons; I, out of my duty, and obligation, to giue a juſt applauſe vnto your reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vertues. And thus I (vvith your <hi>Mary) haue choſen the BETTER part,</hi> to speake <hi>good</hi> of you, and not <hi>euill;</hi> as alſo, therein, <hi>I</hi> ſuſtayn the TRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER part, becauſe your ſelues are not <hi>euill,</hi> but <hi>good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In vvhich aſſurance, and confidence, <hi>I</hi> may boldly
<pb facs="tcp:15355:3"/> defend the luſtre of ſuch excellent LADIES, againſt the miſpriſes of this KNIGHT, attempting to ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish their fame with his pen, which he ſhould main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn with his ſword. A work no leſſe ignoble in him to vndertake, then impoſsible to performe. For, were it not a paradoxicall endeauour, in any man, to accuſe <hi>Pallas</hi> of folly, or <hi>Venus</hi> of deformity, and likewiſe in the reſt, where the perfection of the ſubject preuenteth the credibility of the diſcourſe: Such alſo is the project of this Knight, and ſo improbable is his conceipt; ſince the generall eſteeme, which you haue gayned by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of your liues, hath made you incapable of his wrongs. Neither ſo onely; but, wherein he would ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke you inglorious, therein your glory doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p>VVherefore; <note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>multa mihi fiducia eſt apud vos, multa gloriatio pro vobis;</hi> great is my trust in you, great is my rejoycing for you. Yea I am glad, that I may come vnto you, as my principall defendours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against him, by whom you are equally offended; and that the tempeſt, raiſed againſt me by this Knight, hath driuen me vnto the ſecure harbour of your honourable fauours: whereof though I am vnworthy by my owne deſeruings, yet you can make me worthy by your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious opinions. And <hi>I</hi> conceiue the greater hope thereof, becauſe I am already intitled thereunto by the Knight, ſaying; <note n="e" place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> 
               <hi>it is twenty to one, but ſome of YOVR Ladies will be pearing into this</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">To me, or againſt me rather.</note> 
               <hi>Letter: therefore I will write no more, then I am able to juſtify.</hi> VVhereby your ſelues haue a peculiar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, from his owne hand, to require his <hi>juſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of all thoſe things, which, in his <hi>Letter,</hi> he hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto <hi>your</hi> obſequious, and faithfull ſeruant.</p>
            <p>In which regard, I appeale vnto you (religious, and
<pb facs="tcp:15355:3"/> prudent <hi>LADIES</hi>) and aſsigne you (with your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable leaue) to be my Iudges in this triall; ſince my <hi>CAVSE</hi> is honest, and your ſelues are juſt. She com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, before your preſences, in hir natiue, and naked colours; not painted with eloquence, not adorned with inuention. Our vnhappy Father ſought no <note n="f" place="margin">Geneſ. 3.7</note> 
               <hi>ſigge lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,</hi> while he remayned without ſinne, and (conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) without ſhame. They, that are guiltleſſe, ſeek no colourable defence; for <note n="g" place="margin">Stat. Caecilius.</note> 
               <hi>Innocency is hir owne eloquence,</hi> being eaſily ſuſtayned by hir inward, and proper strength: whereas an euill cauſe requireth much art; being like a statue (or <note n="*" place="margin">Deeſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid, quod intus eſſe oportet. <hi>Plut. in Laconic.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dead carcaſſe</hi>) which hath the ſhape, and proportion of a man, but hath no ſoule within, to giue it life, and motion.</p>
            <p>Finally, therefore, whatſoeuer shall be found defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue in me, let your wiſedome ſupply, or charity for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, ſince he, that offereth vp this little Treatiſe vnto your acceptance, hath alſo dedicated himſelf vnto your ſeruice; remayning now, and euer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humbly deuoted THEOPHILVS HIGGONS.</signed>
               <dateline>ROAN.
<date>
                     <hi>12.</hi> Decemb. <hi>1609.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE PREFACE VNTO THE READER.</hi> VVherein The Method, and Matter, of Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> Letter, and this Apology, are briefly noted.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Readers;</p>
            <p>Hauing granted forth a <hi>Prohibition</hi> againſt my pen, out of the Court of my reaſon, not to intermeddle in that, which belongeth not really, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, vnto my Cauſe; I will omitt all other circumſtances, contayned in the <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 1.2.3.4.5.6.7.</note> Preface of Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> Letter, and examine onely, at this time, what Method, and Matter he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected therein, and prepared for his enſuing diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pag.</hi> 7.</note>
               <hi>My whole diſcourſe</hi> (ſaith i he) <hi>ſhall conſist of ſix Paragraffes. In the FIRST, The cauſe of your Aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhal be ſifted. In the SECOND, Your mayn rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Purgatory diſprooued. In the THIRD, Your prime Father</hi> (S. Auguſtine) <hi>anſwered. In the FOVRTH, your prime Protestant,</hi> D. Humfrey, <hi>defended. In the</hi> FIFT, <hi>The contrary poſition maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. In the SIXT, and laſt, A friendly retreate ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:4"/>
            <p>All which Sections, or <hi>Paragraphs,</hi> may be reduced vnto three principall heads. The <hi>firſt,</hi> vnto MORALL points of honeſty, pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto the VVill. The <hi>ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, fift,</hi> and <hi>ſixt,</hi> vnto INTELLECTVALL points (of Faith, Science, and Opinion) pertayning vnto the Vnderſtanding. The <hi>third,</hi> and <hi>fourth,</hi> are refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mixtly vnto them both; being partly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and partly Intellectuall.</p>
            <p>According to this proportion, and meaſure, I haue made the diſtribution of this Treatiſe. But foraſmuch as praiſe, and diſpraiſe belong rather vnto things <hi>Morall,</hi> then <hi>Intellectuall</hi> (whence it is, that an errour in the later, is more pardonable, then in the former) in the FIRST Part of this Apology, I will take a ſuruay of Sir <hi>Edvvards firſt</hi> ſection, or Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph: in the SECOND, I wil conſider his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and exactneſſe in his <hi>third,</hi> and <hi>fourth</hi> Paragraphs: in the THIRD, and laſt part, I will viſite his <hi>ſecond, fift,</hi> and <hi>ſixt</hi> Paragraphs; wherein I ſhall repreſent vnto you the truth, and ſubſtance of his diſputes. In which THREE parts, I will temper my ſtile with ſobriety, and moderation: VVhereby you, and Sir <hi>Edvvard</hi> him ſelf, may well perceiue, that the neceſſity of defence, and not deſire of reuendge, inuited me vnto this little payn.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:5"/>
            <p>THE FIRST PART; Concerning the MORALL points, obiected vnto me by SIR EDVV. in his FIRST PARAGRAPH.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15355:5"/>
               <head>CHAPTER I. Of my Puritaniſme, and cauſes of my Alienation; pretended by the Knight.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§. 1. <hi>Of my</hi> Puritaniſme.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>HILOSOPHY doth teach, and experience doth prooue, that, amongſt other conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of <hi>Sight,</hi> there is required a conuenient diſtance betwixt the Organ of ſeeing, and the Object to be ſeene: not too farr; becauſe the power of the ſight is limited, and confined vnto a certayn ſpace: not too neere; becauſe the <hi>species</hi> (the formes, or shapes) of the Obiect muſt haue ſufficient ayre, as the meane, to deriue, and conuaigh them vnto the Organ. That is to ſay (in a more familiar kind of ſpeach, for the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of euery Reader) VVe can not diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne a thing, which is too remote from the eye, or placed <note n="*" place="margin">Senſibile po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum ſupra ſenſum, toli<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> ſenſationem.</note> immediately vpon the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This obſeruation may be very beneficiall vnto Sir <hi>Edward;</hi> who (being no <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.9</note> SEER by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration) hath been very much deceiued in his <hi>ſight;</hi> not onely betwixt <note n="b" place="margin">VVhere he dateth his <hi>Letter</hi> to me.</note> 
                     <hi>Queenburrow,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:15355:6"/> 
                     <hi>S. Omers,</hi> where the diſtance was too great, but alſo betwixt the <note n="c" place="margin">VVere he dateth his <hi>Letter</hi> to the Ladies.</note> BLACK FRYARS, and <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> where the diſtance was too little for him, to perceiue the truth of thoſe things, which he imputeth vnto my charge. And the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore, if I, or any other, would dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; VVhy Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> liuing in the circuite of the <hi>Black Friars</hi> (that is to ſay, in the middeſt of a zealous, and religious Congregation) ſhould vntruly accuſe me of <hi>Puritaniſme</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet?</hi> the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution may be this; <hi>The places were ſo neere, that he could not ſee the truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. But I will not ſeparate thoſe things, which he hath joyned together. Behold then (good Reader) the whole connexion of his diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; for I will not be an vnkind <hi>Atropos</hi> to cutt the thred in ſunder, before it be ſpunne out vnto the fartheſt length.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 12.</note> 
                     <q>That famous Colledge of <hi>Christs Church in Oxford</hi> (which you haue ill repayed for the ſweet milk, which you haue ſucked out of hir breaſts) hath not yet forgotten how you were euer ſtayned with <hi>Puritaniſme;</hi> how violently aduerſe you were to all ſuch, as were ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to fauour the Romish Sea. She doth yet ſmile to think, what payn you took, being Cenſour of the houſe, in putting your and to the ſawing downe of a poore, harmeleſſe <hi>May-pole,</hi> becauſe you thought it came out of a <hi>Romish</hi> forreſt. VVhen you were Lecturer at <note n="*" place="margin">Fleetſir.</note> S. <hi>Dunſtanes,</hi> your contributory Auditours thought your long prayer, and ſpitting pawſes too ſhort, becauſe the reuerend Bishopps (yea
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15355:6"/> euen your owne Lord, and Maiſter) were euer left out for wranglers, and <hi>Antichriſtian Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies,</hi> not worthy to be named, in the ſame day, with your holy Paſtours, and ſanctified Miniſters. Thus haue you euer affected ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity. But how commeth it to paſſe, that you should now fall into the oppoſite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariety? &amp;c.</q> So he.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Here <hi>Puritaniſme</hi> is made the <hi>Aries</hi> to rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the walls of my credit; and, being an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent vntruth, is placed in the very front, and <hi>forlorne-hope,</hi> of his future aſſault; that ſo my chandge might ſeeme either impoſſible, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, where the <hi>termini</hi> are ſo diſtant, and, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, the motion muſt be long: howbeit the proportion is not iuſt herein, betwixt corporall, and ſpirituall things.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. But, to deale orderly without confuſion, and plainely without obſcurity, in the roote of this accuſation, vpon which the branches of the reſt depend; I will firſt conſider the point it ſelf, or crime of <hi>Puritaniſme,</hi> obiected vnto me by the Knight: ſecondly I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiew the proofes, which he alleadgeth to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. FIRST then for this PVRITANISME; I will readily confeſſe, with Sir Edward, that it is a <hi>ſtayne:</hi> but I conſtantly deny, that it was, or could be ſo, vnto me, who embraced PROTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTINISME (as, in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, it diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth from the note of a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Purita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi>) and eſteemed it to be more probable in reaſon, as I ſaw it to be more conformable vnto the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15355:7"/> State.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Of which my vnderſtanding, and affection in theis affayres, as my conſcience is my beſt witneſſe, ſo I want not ſondry ouertures to declare the ſame, if my publick aſſociation, if my priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, if Lectures, if Sermons, if, finally, any outward act may teſtify my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thoughts, wherein Sir <hi>Edward</hi> hath no intereſt to be my Iudge.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. If I muſt yet make a more particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, it ſhall be vnto my Reuerend Lord, the L. Bishopp of <hi>London</hi> himſelf; for, as he knew me better then this Knight, ſo he knew like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that <hi>a ſtayned Puritan</hi> was vnfitt either to receiue his fauours, or to do him Seruice; wherein ſondry occaſions preſented themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vnto me, to encounter PVRITANS; and yet they can not (or, if they can, let them) ſay, that openly, or ſecretely, in whole, or in part, in doctrine, diſcipline, or ceremony, I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable vnto their ſide.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. VVherefore, to come, SECONDLY, vnto Sir <hi>Edward</hi> his <hi>proofes</hi> of this pretended ſtayne (for, if it be ſufficient for him to accuſe, I ſhall not be innocent) I confeſſe the <hi>Fact</hi> it ſelf in his firſt proof, but I deny it in the ſecond.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Firſt then (Sir <hi>Edward</hi>) vnto your firſt; I confeſſe the fact, which you alleadge, I deny the cauſe, which you aſſigne. For the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and proper motiue of my diſconceipt againſt that <hi>harmeleſſe</hi> Maypole (whereof I was the Aduerſary, &amp; you are the Aduocate) was, <hi>becauſe</hi> it came out of the Colledge grounds;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15355:7"/> taken thence by ſtealth, and erected (with ſcorne) neere vnto our walls, without our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and this alſo to juſtify a former wrong, lately offered in the ſame kind. This was the cauſe (as many can yet remember) firſt moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing me vnto that enterpriſe; which, though it were not expedient for me then to vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, yet (being a woode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proof in your behalf) it was not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for you to mention at this time.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. As for your ſecond proof; it is more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, and materiall. And now I am glad to ſee your <hi>writt of remoouall,</hi> whereby you bring my cauſe from <hi>Oxford,</hi> to receiue a triall at <hi>London.</hi> For as this injury is more marqueable, ſo is my defence more ample in this caſe.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. VVherefore I appeale vnto you, Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Rightworſhipfull, and other, well reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, Auditours (from whom as I haue had many, and ſingular tokens of your loue, ſo I recognize it heere, with my beſt thanks) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you, in your election of me vnto the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of your PREACHER, or whether I, from the firſt vnto the laſt performance of that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, gaue any ſignification of theis things, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof I am now accuſed?</p>
                  <p n="14">14. But if in the manner, and matter of my Sermons; if in the compoſition, and ſtyle, and other appurtenances of ſpeach, I euer expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a contrary affection vnto that, which is heere impoſed vpon me; if vſually, in my ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Lectures (and, alwayes, in a more ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aſſembly) I made a generall remembrance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15355:8"/> of the <hi>Bishopps,</hi> and a ſpeciall of my Lord, and Maiſter; if I were different in habit, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment from the ſingularity of <hi>ſtayned Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans;</hi> laſtly, if I ſhewed a totall conformity in regular demeanure, why ſhould this whole fable, compounded of ſo many vntrue cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, be ſo improbably ſuggeſted againſt me by the Knight? Surely this benefitt enſueth vnto me by ſuch a wrong, that <hi>Fame</hi> deſerueth little creditt in things more ſecrete, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, ſince it is controlled in things ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and cleare.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. I might alſo heere produce, for more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant refutation of this pretended <hi>ſtayn,</hi> a certayn prouerbiall report (intertayned by my good friends) of the <hi>oppoſite contrariety;</hi> viz. <hi>If any man will heare a Popish Sermon, let him go to S. Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtanes.</hi> I might acquaynt you with many po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, deliuered by me there, in freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toryes, which are <hi>Hereticall</hi> in GENEVA, but <hi>Catholique</hi> in ROME. I might appeale vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quality; Clericall, Laicall; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vnlearned; noble, baſe; &amp;c. who accuſed me in the later, but euer freed me in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer reſpect. And, if farther occaſion ſhall be miniſtred vnto me, I may (perhapps) deale more punctually therein.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Meane while, thus much ſhall ſuffiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this <hi>Puritanicall ſtayn;</hi> which, though it doth more properly belong vnto things IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TELLECTVALL, then MORALL, yet ſince it is here taken by Sir <hi>Edvvard</hi> into his <hi>ſifting Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph,</hi> with reference vnto the ſequele (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15355:8"/> he ſeuerely examineth <hi>the cauſes of my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienation</hi>) I could not pretermitt it in this place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 2.</hi> Of the cauſes of my Alienation; and particularly of <hi>Debts.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>BVt how commeth it to paſſe</hi> (ſaith Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) that you should now fall into the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite" contrariety?</hi> His anſwere is. <note n="e" place="margin">pag. <hi>14.</hi> &amp;c</note> 
                     <hi>Happily you haue done this either wholly to eſcape, or to agree the better with your CREDITOVRS. Happily, hauing miſſed a former PREFERMENT, you think, by this meanes, to be wooed by the State to returne. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily the yoke of VVEDLOCK, being ſomewhat bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to your shoulders, was an induceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to make you caſt off the plough.</hi> And is it, but <hi>happily,</hi> ſo? Behold his gradation. SVRELY, <hi>not onely ſome, but euen all of theis, were the cords, that haled on your</hi> FIRST MOTIVE.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But hold your hand, good Sir, a while; you muſt not object, and anſwere alſo; and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth me now to interpoſe my ſelf, leaſt your <hi>anſwere</hi> heere, might be more prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall vnto me, then your <hi>objection</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">§. 1. <hi>num.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.</note> before. VVherefore I will intreate particularly of your three aſſigned cauſes of my Alienation, and firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the matter of <hi>Debts;</hi> which (as you <note n="f" place="margin">Ibid.</note> ſay) <hi>the world knoweth were very cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours:</hi> agayn; <note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 19.</note> 
                     <hi>It was the grimme aſpect of your owne eſtate, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. As for your amplifications <hi>(the world kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth: clamorous: grimme aspect)</hi> they may be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes of your <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rhetori</hi> conceſſum eſt ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentijs vti falſis, &amp;c. <hi>Gell.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> rhetoricall veyne; and ſo, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:15355:9"/> them paſſe, I come vnto the matter of your accuſation, which will eaſily vaniſh into ſmoke, and returne into that <hi>Nothing,</hi> out of which it was taken, and made, if you will vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chſafe to conſider with me, <hi>Firſt,</hi> the quantity of theis debts; <hi>Secondly,</hi> the reaſon of the ſame; <hi>Thirdly,</hi> my meanes of diſchardge; <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the diſpoſition, and quality of my Creditours; <hi>Fiftly,</hi> and laſtly, my honeſt inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion to repay. Thus I doubt not, but Sir <hi>Edward</hi> shall recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a juſt ſatisfaction; whereby alſo I shall ſtoppe the wide mouth of his world.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Concerning the FIRST; it may be, that <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi> hath putt my debts to vſury, and made the increaſe greater then the principall; which, by many pounds, extendeth not vnto one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred marks.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Concerning the SECOND; it may pleaſe Sir <hi>Edward</hi> to vnderſtand, that my debts (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer) aroſe not vpon any vitious courſe of life, but vpon other reſpects, incident vnto Schollers, and ſuch, eſpecially, whom either continuall attendance about their Lords, or euident hope of better fortunes, inuiteth vnto a more liberall expenſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Concerning the THIRD therefore; Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> world may beare witneſſe for me, that though my deſert (hauing no value in it ſelf) could be of no more value, then it was made by the loue, and kindneſſe of others; yet, as my poſſibility, and probability of imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t were very great) in that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect) ſo they, whoſe fauour nouriſhed my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15355:9"/> in a comfortable expectation (beyond ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of my ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k) would not ſuffer me to fall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a burthen of ſo little waight.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Concerning the FOVRTH then; if my Creditours had bene as violent, as that <note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.27.28.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull ſeruant, who, forgetting his Maiſters patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce toward himſelf; ſhewed impatience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne fellow; yet were they ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo, that they would deſtroy the fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which ſhould be common vnto vs both? No; that, which they lent to buyld me vp, they demanded not to pull me downe, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected my harueſt, wherein they might reape their owne agayn; if with aduantage, it depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon my will, which (being not like the barren ground, wherein the ſeed is loſt, but like the fertile, which yealdeth it agayn with profit) hath euer been more apt to recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce a benefitt, then to retayn a due.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Wherefore, for the FIFT point (which, in conſequence, doth chiefly import me) I am deſirous to ſatisfy Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> and his world, therein, in all ſyncerity of heart. But becauſe <note n="i" place="margin">Pro.</note> 
                     <hi>the heart of man is deepe,</hi> and is knowen onely (infallibly) vnto him, <note n="k" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.</note> 
                     <hi>who walketh in all our ſecrete paths</hi> (or vnto none, farther then he will communicate the ſame) I appeale firſt, and principally, vnto my great, and ſouereigne Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, by whom, and before whom, I muſt, and may juſtify my honeſt inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion in this behalf. If I am guilty, he is the Accuſer that ſhall be the Witneſſe, and he is the witneſſe that ſhall be the Iudge, and he is the judge that ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15355:10"/> me, and from his ſentence there lieth no appeale. Here then is my confidence, and comfort.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Howbeit, ſince Charity will think the beſt in all things, and of all men (for <note n="l" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5</note> 
                     <hi>ſhe thinketh not euill</hi>) and, ſpecially, when ſhe hath probable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements thereunto; I am glad that they (Men) who (alone) can accuſe me vnjuſtly, may (and ought) juſtly excuſe me alſo. For, as at ſondry times before, and vnto ſondry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, I did fully, and thankfully repay my debts, ſo, vpon my departure out of <hi>England,</hi> I gaue ſome tokens of my morall inclination in this kind.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. I will not (though I might) go vnto <hi>Oxford</hi> for my proof, but vnto <hi>London,</hi> whither I was cited <note n="*" place="margin">§. 1. <hi>Num.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.</note> before, for a triall in the firſt, and fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall objection, contriued by Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> ſkill. And now, becauſe he ſhall not farther call into queſtion, nor diſprooue, my fidelity, and truth; I am compelled to name ſome men (the firſt being one of my beſt, the other none of my worſt friends) viz <note n="†" place="margin">In Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lane.</note> 
                     <hi>M. Garth,</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>M. Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotts,</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Neere Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring croſſe.</note> 
                     <hi>M. Councell:</hi> to whom (conjunctiuely) I diſchardged the ſumme of eight pounds, or more; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no neceſsity (but honeſty) did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce me thereunto. Whence Sir <hi>Edward</hi> (out of his <note n="m" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Charity</hi>) may reaſonably collect, and credibly affirme, that, in borrowing, I had no purpoſe to deceiue.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. And heere, though it may ſeeme repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vnto the duty, and affection of a Sonne, to detract any eſtimation from his Fathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,
<pb facs="tcp:15355:10"/> yet ſince his <note n="*" place="margin">Annexed vnto Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Letter</hi> is publiſhed to giue more creditt, and authority vnto Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> calumniations, yea <hi>to ſatisfy any vnprejudicate Reader</hi> (for ſo the <note n="†" place="margin">In his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monit.</note> Printer teſtifieth in his name) and laſtly, ſince heere the matter it ſelf doth ineuitably challendge it at my hands (for though there are other vntrue points contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that Letter, either as much, or more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall vnto me then this, yet I will ſeek no occaſion to contradict any parcell thereof, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then it ſhall preſent it ſelf vnto me; nor yet will I accept it farther, then pure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity ſhall conſtrayne me) I muſt remooue a ſcandall, which, by virtue of the ſayd Letter, may (perhappes) make a deepe impreſsion in ſome mens hearts, to my ſingular inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and loſſe.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Whereas therefore, you (my deare, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father) giue this ſignification in your <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (bearing the forme of an indictment againſt me, your Sonne) viz. <hi>before he went beyond the Seas, he borrowed diuers ſummes of money, with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (I am perſwaded) neuer to repay them, and, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, he abuſed my ſelf for ten pound;</hi> the former inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces (beſides many other proofes) may <hi>perſwade</hi> you otherwiſe, and aſſure you of that, which a Father doth leaſt ſuſpect, or leaſt accuſe; to witt, the <hi>Morall honeſly</hi> of your Sonne: which, by the courſe of nature, hath, from you, deſcended vnto me, as my beſt inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. And that it may appeare vnto your ſelf, and others (who, either by your owne conſent, or by Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> fault, haue intereſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15355:11"/> in theis accuſations, to require my defence) that I did not <hi>abuſe</hi> your Fatherly benignity (which emptied your meanes to fill my wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as freely, as <note n="n" place="margin">
                        <hi>S.</hi> Aug. Conf. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Patricius</hi> himſelf dealt with his <hi>Augustine</hi>) I pray you to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that, which you did (or might) know lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before: to witt, that I borrowed, and receiued the ſayd <hi>ten pounds</hi> of you, to further my ſuite in obtayning a <note n="*" place="margin">S. Michaels in Glouceſter.</note> Benefice, being in his Majeſties gift, and vacant vpon the depriuation of the late In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent <hi>(ſtayned with Puritaniſme)</hi> and that I was expreſſly counſayled thereunto by my Honorable Lord; howbeit, vpon ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, I ſurceaſed from the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. This was the occaſion of borrowing that ſumme. But now, if you will compare the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me alſo, when I borrowed it, with the time of my departure out of <hi>England,</hi> I may be fully cleared from all ſuſpition of <hi>abuſe.</hi> For my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, out of <hi>England,</hi> being in Nouember 1607. and the receipt of that money, about Eaſter 1606. the diſtance of the times doth prooue, that my intention was not fraudule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; ſince at Eaſter 1606. I thought not of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture in Nouember 1607; which was (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) two yeares after.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. So then it is true, that I borrowed ſundry ſummes, in generall, and this, in particular alſo, <hi>before I went beyond the Seas:</hi> but this word (BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE) is heere ambiguous (and, in one ſenſe, very prejudiciall) and therefore muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed: viz. <hi>Mediately,</hi> or <hi>Immediately</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. If it be taken <hi>mediately,</hi> as it ſignifieth a good diſtance of time, I confeſſe the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15355:11"/> in this ſenſe, to be very true; but then my honeſt intention receiueth little, or no prejudice thereby. If it be taken <hi>immediately,</hi> as it ſignifieth a propinquity, and neereneſſe of time; I muſt deny the accuſation, in this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, to be true; and this, onely, is it, which can be prejudiciall vnto the honeſty of my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude then; I ſay, and, vpon my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I proteſt vnto you, that neither immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, nor neere vpon my departure, nor after my firſt reſolution that way, did I borrow any money, but I did repay ſome; and ſo, in each reſpect (both <hi>of not borrowing,</hi> and <hi>of repaying</hi>) I am freed from the infamy of this pretended <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe;</hi> foraſmuch as I might then haue borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more, and I might not haue repayed any: both which had been to my great aduantadge, when money was to be my beſt (if not my onely) friend.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Now, if my true defence were not thus plainely, and articulately ſet downe, who would not conceiue the meaning to be this? viz. <hi>Immediately before, or vpon his departure, he bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed diuers ſummes of money, &amp;c.</hi> For, by the contempering, and mingling together of theis words, <hi>borrow; abuſe; neuer repay; going beyond the ſeas;</hi> this ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe muſt neceſſarily flow, &amp; iſſue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reout: and this, I know, is the conſtruction, which is made by many, and ſpecially by them, whoſe will doth make them more credulous in this caſe. <note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>Caeſar</hi> in commentar. Et Lamprid. in Heliogab.</note> 
                     <hi>Quod volumus, facilè credimus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">16. But there is more art, then charity in theis commixtions; which are as preiudiciall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15355:12"/> vnto thoſe, whom we are willing to defame, as the conjunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> with a more beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne, &amp; happy ſtarr, is fatall vnto the bodies in our inferiour world. As for example. CLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT the eight (of bleſſed life, and happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory) is accuſed by <note n="p" place="margin">de Antichr.</note> 
                     <hi>M. Gabriel Powell,</hi> of <hi>whoredome.</hi> When? <hi>Ante Papatum</hi> (ſayth he) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Popedome. Who is the witneſſe? Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour <hi>Gentilis;</hi> his profeſſed enemy. Well; be it ſo: it was in his yong<note n="*" place="margin">of <hi>16</hi> years.</note>age (as D. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilis</hi> related it vnto me) wherein, and <note n="q" place="margin">Confeſſ. l. <hi>6</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note> after which, <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> himſelf confeſſeth, and lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter follies. But yet; why ante <hi>Papatum?</hi> Why ſhould his <hi>Papacy</hi> (or <hi>the</hi> Papacy rather) in his declining age, beare the fault of his youthfull yeares? This was an euill commixtion alſo, &amp;, for the manner, it hath a ſingular reſemblance with the other, whereof I haue already trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and wherewith I will conclude this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. Finally therefore; as my Religion, and diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do powerfully incline me to <hi>GIVE euery man his owne</hi> (which is the proper act of <hi>Iustice,</hi> but not of <hi>Charity;</hi> which doth <hi>FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIVE euery man his debts;</hi> and for this cauſe, though I will pay others, yet I will ſpare Sir <hi>Edward</hi>) ſo I will endeauour, to my power, to giue a iuſt ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto my Creditours, whether <note n="*" place="margin">See before; num. <hi>2. 3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>clamorous,</hi> or ſilent. Vnto the firſt (if there be any ſuch) I would owe nothing but loue: vnto the ſecond, I owe more loue then before. I know the precept, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> 
                     <note n="r" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8.</note> giueth, viz. <hi>Owe nothing vnto any man, but this,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15355:12"/> that you loue one an other.</hi> I know that it is a mark, which <hi>Dauid</hi> 
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.21</note> ſetteth vpon the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man; <hi>he borroweth, and payeth not agayn.</hi> My deſire to obſerue that precept, and to avoyd this mark, ſhall expreſſe it ſelf in my carefull, and induſtrious prouiſion for that little quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of debt, which Sir <hi>Edward</hi> eſteemeth to be a great cauſe of my <hi>Alienation</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Church. But whether there be any porportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwixt the cauſe, and the effect, I will now remitt my ſelf, &amp; him, vnto the deciſion of the impartiall Reader.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>3.</hi> Want of Preferment.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. I come now vnto the ſecond <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which is like vnto the firſt; as, amongſt <note n="*" place="margin">Facies non omnibus vna est, Nec di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa tamen, &amp;c. <hi>Ouid.</hi>
                     </note> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the one is the half image of the other. <hi>The Miſſe of your preferment was grieuous vnto you,</hi> ſaith <note n="t" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</note> Sir <hi>Edward:</hi> and; <note n="u" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 14.</note> 
                     <hi>hauing miſſed a former preferment, you think, by this meanes, that the State will wooe you to returne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In which accuſation he is ſo confident, that, diuiding the affection of <hi>Aërius</hi> vnto me, &amp; reſeruing the opinion of that heretick vnto <note n="w" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 56.</note> himſelf, he <note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 20.</note> challengeth me, as a man <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the diſeaſe of Aërius:</hi> and; <note n="y" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <hi>this was the diſeaſe of Aërius;</hi> and, <note n="z" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</note> 
                     <hi>when I ſpeake of Aërius, I think of M.</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">An hater of God.</note> 
                     <hi>Theomiſus.</hi> Which name Sir <hi>Edward</hi> giueth me in his new baptiſme: and I am no more vnfortunate therein, then <hi>S. Innocentius,</hi> whom the Magdeburgians haue bated the firſt ſyllable of his name; or S. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Trinitarian</hi> hereticks haue added one letter;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15355:13"/> or <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> with whom a Pagan Philoſopher exchandged an other; making them appeare as <note n="†" place="margin">Nocentius. Sathanaſius. Caprianus.</note> monſters, who were <hi>the lights of the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. But digeſting this wrong (as alſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; viz. <note n="❀" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Fantaſticall witt,</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">10.</note> 
                     <hi>frantick fitts,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">50.</note> 
                     <hi>ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Rabſhekah;</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">6.</note> 
                     <hi>monstrous birth, &amp;c.</hi> and ſparing the Authour, who accuſeth <note n="d" place="margin">49.</note> 
                     <hi>my curriſh pen,</hi> I proceed vnto the matter it ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And heere, if Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> former objectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (of <hi>Puritaniſme</hi>) had ſtood in force againſt me; it had not bene ſo much a mutation, as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion, and perfection in that ghoſpell, to runne, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, into <hi>Browniſne,</hi> or <hi>Barrowiſme,</hi> and, from thence, into <hi>Anabaptiſme;</hi> which, in the ſtrict letter, ſenſed by inward Spiritt (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ancient rules of <hi>Protestant</hi> Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo) is the neateſt, and moſt refined ghoſpell of them, who fell away from <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taries,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptists</hi> fell from vs &amp;c. <hi>Luth.</hi> in Gal. 5.9.</note> LVTHER, the <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Powel</hi> de Antichr. <hi>pag.</hi> 324.</note> 
                     <hi>great Reformer</hi> of the Church. And ſurely, if the chandge of my Religion had depended v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch a temporall reſpect, as Sir <hi>Edward</hi> doth ſuggeſt, thoſes courſes had ſorted as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my commodity, and more neerely with my conſcience, then this <hi>oppoſite contrariety,</hi> which I now embrace.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. But I plead no ſuch defence. It was the light of truth, that conuinced me; the power of grace, that perſwaded me; no corrupt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but euident reaſon, no wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in earth, but deſire of heauen, no diſcontentment, which I found, but comfort, which I ſought, did bring me, effectually, vnto this happy chandge.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15355:13"/>6. Which motion of my Soule, if it came from the earth, and had the ſame beginning with this corruptible Body; my choyce were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouident to forſake my former, and to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn this preſent courſe. Could I not perceiue, that, by flying, I did not fly, but increaſe my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill? Did I not know, that this was no ſalue for ſuch a ſore, but a remedy worſe then the ſickneſſe it ſelf, if either I wanted, or ſought for temporall meanes? Did I not foreſee, that I ſhould now exclude my ſelf from ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent meanes, as I had, and better fortunes, which I expected; and that, withall, I ſhould expoſe my name vnto certayn obloquy, and my life vnto vncertayn danger?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Oh, ſayth the Knight, but <hi>you thought, that the Sate would wooe you to returne.</hi> No, not ſo: for am I not as a droppe of water in that great Element? But yet, you (Sir <hi>Edward</hi>) a member of <note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>the moſt ſuperlatiue Parliament,</hi> do you not (in charity) perſwade my returne, and do you not frame ſondry <note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 94.</note> Motiues to this effect?</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Your <note n="h" place="margin">pag. <hi>4.</hi> &amp;c.</note> former lines were written in bloud (as the lawes of <hi>Draco</hi>) your later in milk; wherein I am reſtored agayn vnto my <note n="i" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 93.</note> name <hi>(Theophilus)</hi> and (almoſt) vnto your fauour; ſo that you, my Aduerſary-Friend, might juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue a ſecond right in me (the firſt being alwayes reſerued vnto my Honorable Lord) to vſe, diſpoſe, and employ me according to your will, if my conſcience did not retayn me in this Faith, with an inuiolable bond.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. As for other Motiues, more effectuall, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15355:14"/> powerable, then fleſh, and bloud can eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, I will ſay nothing at this time. I may not publiſh the fauours of other men ſo freely, as Sir <hi>Edward</hi> doth proclayme my faults. This onely may ſuffiſe to ſhew vnto men of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and reaſonable mindes, that I languiſhed not with <hi>the diſeaſe of</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Epiph. <hi>hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 75. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. <hi>haereſ.</hi> 53.</note> AERIVS (or <note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>See the</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Fox his Calend. Ianuar. 1.</note> WICK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIFFE) and delighted not my ſelf in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of opinion (as they did) but, for the truths ſake, which conuinced me, for my ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſake, which lay in perill, for my Sauiours ſake, who redeemed it with his bloud, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred vnto that <note n="m" place="margin">Hieronym. ad Damaſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Ark,</hi> out of which there is no ſafety in the waues of hereſy, and ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; that ſo I might be knitt vnto that Church, whereof, <note n="n" place="margin">
                        <hi>In</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
                     <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> ſayth, DAMASVS was <hi>Rectour</hi> in his time; and PAVL is at this day: a Church <hi>one</hi> in faith, <hi>ancient</hi> in time, <hi>viſible</hi> in ſucceſſion, <hi>comely</hi> in order, <hi>conformable</hi> in actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; <note n="*" place="margin">It was S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> obſeruation in his time.</note> ſhe, that is in all places, and like hir ſelf, whereſoeuer ſhe is; the <hi>roote,</hi> without which the branches ſhall wither; the vnited body, out of which the diuided members ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and decay.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§. 4. <hi>Of my</hi> Wife; <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. THe third <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which Sir <hi>Edward</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth of my Alienatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is my Mariad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge; <hi>a yoke</hi> (ſaith <note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</note> he) <hi>to burthenſome to your ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; the mariadge-God, Himenaeus, was none of your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15355:14"/> beſt friends, &amp;c.</hi> Concerning which ſubject, I might intertayn the Reader with a long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. But, <hi>cui bono?</hi> as <hi>Caſsius</hi> was wont to ſay: <hi>to what good,</hi> or for what end, and purpoſe?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Seeing two ſorts of people, generally, in the world; <hi>Good,</hi> and <hi>Euill: VViſe,</hi> and <hi>Fooliſh: Charitable,</hi> and <hi>Malitious;</hi> I haue caſt my recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thus: <hi>I ſhall not be condemned by the firſt,</hi> and, <hi>I care not to be accuſed by the ſecond.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Howbeit, to ſatisfy the juſt expectation of ſome, &amp; idle curioſity of others, in this matter; I ſay, that I ſought not my Wife in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but was ſought by hir friends; Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of quality, able, and willing to further me in the courſes of this world, and ſpecially in my late profeſſion. I accepted their conditions, and liked hirs; the promiſe was made, the knot was tied: yet ſo, that ſhe was to remayn, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnder their prouiſion, vntill I ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually poſſeſſed with all conuenient meanes: and then hir portion was to be in my hands, hir ſelf in my care.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Now, if Sir <hi>Edward</hi> will preſſe me yet farther with that vnciuill dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the <note n="p" place="margin">A. Gellius <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 20</note> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Cenſor; <hi>Habéſne vxorem ex animi tuiſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ?</hi> I might anſwere vnto him, as the party vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cenſor: <hi>Habeo equidem vxorem, ſed non herclé ex animi tui ſententiâ.</hi> It was inough for him, and me, to make our choyce, to our ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne contentment, in this caſe. If there were any other default, Sir <hi>Edward</hi> knoweth the wiſe, &amp; neceſſary counſayle for me, and other huſbands alſo: <note n="q" place="margin">A. Gell. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Vxoris vitium aut tollendum, aut
<pb facs="tcp:15355:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> ferendum: qui tollit, vxorem commodiorem praeſtat; qui fert, ſeſe meliorem facit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. But to deale with you, in good earneſt; Sir: do not think ſo vncharitably of me, that I wanted due affection vnto my ſpouſe, or, that wanting due affection vnto hir, I would <hi>therefore</hi> renounce the <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt;</hi> as you pretend your Church to be, &amp; inueſt hir with that name. No; there had been other alleuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in this behalf, not ſo vnkind to hir, not ſo diſhoneſt before men, not ſo impious in the ſight of God. But, that I might embrace a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vnion with the Spouſe of Chriſt (the <hi>Catholick, Romane, Apoſtolick</hi> Church) I am <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> ſeparated by place (not loue) from hir, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt whom, and me, there is a perfect nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneſſe in this great diſtance. And though Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> pen hath made a <note n="*" place="margin">See after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Chap. <hi>2. §. 3.</hi> num. <hi>22. 25.</hi>
                     </note> fowle blott to the prejudice of hir good affection towards me, yet I will belieue it to be a part of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrongs, which we ſuſtayn from this vngentle Knight. And thus aſſuring both hir, and him, that I want not affection, but meanes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it (which <hi>I</hi> will endeauour to do, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within, or without the Land) I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this matter, and, therewith, this chapter alſo.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Perhapps now, I may be condemned for writing too much, or too little in this kind; howbeit, he, that ingageth me into the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cenſure of the Readers, hath made the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me aduenture of his owne fortune. If we fare equally, I am eaſed by his company. If I fare
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15355:15"/> worſe, I haue patience to beare, and charity to forgiue. If better, he hath no reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playn.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of ſondry other crimes, objected vnto me by Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> in his firſt <hi>(ſifting)</hi> Paragraph.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 1.</hi> Of my diſconceipt toward the <hi>Catholique, Romane</hi> faith, after my Alienation from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. SIR; the amplitude of your diſcourſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the commiſſion of your title. For though your firſt Paragraph doth promiſe (according to the inſcription)<note n="r" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>to fift the</hi> CAV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES <hi>of my Alienation</hi> (which you haue rayſed vnto THREE) yet the greater part thereof ſpendeth it ſelf in other prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded crimes; viz. <hi>diſconceipt toward my preſent Religion; perjury in promiſes; aſtorgy, and vnnaturall affection vnto my Father;</hi> and ſuch like: things without cohere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in them ſelues, or reference vnto their title: &amp; yet, Sir, you accuſe the <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>miſhapen diſproportion</hi> of my booke; as though my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipts had pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the womb of my braynes, and, ſtriuing for birth, had broken from me rather by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, then by order. Which accuſation may (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happs) belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g rather vnto your ſelf, whoſe zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le to do me wrong, diſtempered the method of your thoughts; ſo that the things, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15355:16"/> to proceed from you at the firſt, retired themſelues to yeald paſſadge vnto the reſt: as <note n="t" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Zara</hi> beganne firſt to come into the world, and yet withdrew himſelf, to giue place vnto the birth of <hi>Pharez.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. But I paſſe by your method, and I come vnto your Matter; wherein if you be found de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue alſo, either by your owne inuention (which is good) or by others ſuggeſtion (which I would rather belieue, in this caſe) then your <hi>ſtayning</hi> calumniations muſt, in the end, returne, and ebb agayn vpon you (or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) from whom they flowed in the beginning. And now I will treate particularly of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended crimes; which, being diſperſed in your <hi>ſifting</hi> Paragraph, ſhall be reduced heere, more exactly, vnto their ſeuerall heads.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The FIRST criminatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore (annexed vnto the former <hi>Cauſes</hi>) toucheth my diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt toward the <hi>Romane, Catholick</hi> faith: as though my <hi>Alienation</hi> from you, were rather in actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; outward, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inward; in mouth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mynd: &amp; this you prooue by a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <q>FIRST. I do eaſily belieue (ſay <note n="u" place="margin">
                           <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</note> you) vpon his credible report, that at ſuch time, as <hi>M. Etkins</hi> (your old fellow Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layn, and friend) <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>at</hi> S. Omers.</note> deſired your company to <hi>Bruxells,</hi> or to <hi>England,</hi> you ſmote your hand vpon your breaſt, and, in great paſsion, vttered theis words; <hi>O that I might ſafely returne, for that is my deſire.</hi> Yea more; you <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</note> ſay, that, at his ſight, I had <hi>Peters</hi> teares in my eyes, <hi>for the deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of my Maiſter,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15355:16"/>4. As for the perſon relating, he doth me wrong, if you wrong not him in the relation it ſelf. For I appeale vnto his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience (which repreſenteth things paſt, in hir ſecrete, and inward reflex) whether I gaue him the leaſt ſigne, or ſuſpition of inconſtancy in this (tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and onely <hi>Catholick</hi>) faith, or whether I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed any, the leaſt, affection toward that, which he now doth, and I did ſometimes, profeſſe. <q>Doth he not remember, that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, treating with me to ſhew obedience, and humility in hearing the judgements of ſome principall Deuines in <hi>England,</hi> but finding no hope of my conformity, according to his deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſayd thereupon; <hi>VVhat then ſhould he do in England, if he be ſo obſtinate?</hi>
                     </q> Yea, doth he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his owne apology for me, in my Fathers preſence; <hi>In good faith I do belieue, that he is ſo perſwaded in his heart?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. That he propoſed vnto me a jorney for <hi>Bruxells,</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> or both, I deny not; as alſo that I ſhewed an affection in me, loyall vnto my Prince, dutifull vnto my Contrey, louing vnto my Friends (whom I was deſirous to ſee) but yet without any ſuch tragicall action, or paſsion, to any ſuch end, and purpoſe, as you, from him, pretend. Wherefore I muſt leaue you both to deuide this wrong betwixt your ſelues; which is ſo much the greater (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in you, or in him) becauſe you are one, whom I neuer offended; he is one, whom I euer loued. And what ſoeuer the effects of his <hi>friendſhipp</hi> toward me, haue been, they are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15355:17"/> not proportionable vnto this diſcourteſy, if the matter it ſelf were true; as, God knoweth, it is moſt falſe. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid wiſely, vpon his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; <hi>Quidam ſunt amici leues, &amp; inimici graues:</hi> which yet I will neuer apply vnto him, vnleſſe I find, by better informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then you ſeeme either to receiue, or giue, that he hath done me this wrong, which you haue publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in his name. And ſo much for the firſt.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Your <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> SECOND proof enſueth; viz. <note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 17.</note> 
                     <q>The ſmall liking, which you haue to the Romiſh Religion, you ſufficiently manifeſted, when as being reconciled to that Synagogue, by one <hi>Flud,</hi> a Prieſt, you did yet, after your returne out of Yorkeſhire, write a little Pamphlett of Veniall, and Mortall ſinnes, flat againſt the principles of that profeſsion.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. If after Reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the Catholick Church, I had written, or ſpoken againſt any article of hir faith, my crime toward hir, might ſeeme inexpiable, and your aduantage againſt me, very great. Howbeit, it is neither the one, that I am guilty of, nor the other, which I feare; but it was your pleaſure, Sir, to make a chayne of ſuch wrongs, &amp; to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue them in your diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. I anſwere therefore, FIRST; that I wrote not that little Pamphlett, after my returne out of Yorkeſhire, but before. SECONDLY; that as I came vnreconciled into the preſence of that Venerable Prieſt (F. <hi>Flud</hi>) ſo I neuer ſaw him, nor heard of him, vntill my arriuall in S. <hi>Omers;</hi> where alſo himſelf had remayned one whole
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15355:17"/> yeare (at the leaſt) before that time. And I mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, that your intelligencer concealed this point from your notice; which he could not but know much more certainly, then that I was reconciled <hi>by ſuch a Priest:</hi> though heere alſo I leaue your informer, and your ſelf, vnto your better proofes. THIRDLY; that I wrote it according to my opinion therein, preciſely at that howre. And truly this was one of the 3. or 4. points, wherein I had the learned, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, and expedite reſolution of that Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Prieſt, after my arriuall; being perſwaded (abſolutely) in moſt points, at that time, and chiefly in the chiefeſt, &amp; metropoliticall que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, concerning the <note n="❀" place="margin">Men must dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſeek out the <hi>true Church,</hi> that ſo they may <hi>reſt in hir judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſayth <hi>D. Field</hi> in his epist. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat.</note> CHVRCH. So then I neither wrote agaiſt that, which I did belieue, nor yealded vnto that, which I did not concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. FOVRTHLY; that the occaſion of writing it, was a certain conference betwixt me, and a Catholick gentleman; vnto whoſe hands I deliuered it, and deſired him to procure me a good reſolution thereunto. FIFTLY; that the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of publiſhing it, were many, and one principall; viz. to diuert a ſtrong ſuſpition, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayned (ſomewhere) to my prejudice, as I was induced to think by ſondry reaſons. SIXTLY; that ſome particulars in that pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phlet (as namely, <note n="*" place="margin">in fine.</note> 
                     <hi>Secreta mea mihi, &amp;c.</hi> haue long ſince made the conſtruction more cleare vnto Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> and his world, which, ſometimes, was more ſecrete, and obſcure.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. This is (good Readers) the true text of this matter, which now I referr vnto your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15355:18"/> interpretation. Let me add onely a word (for a finall complement herein) and ſay thus much; that if I were as guilty of, or in this fault, as my Accuſer would make you belieue, yet I might be excuſed rather then <note n="y" place="margin">See the <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of <hi>Fox</hi> his Calendar. Part. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>374.</hi> &amp;c.</note> CRANMER himſelf, whoſe ſeuerall Treatiſes <hi>pro, &amp; contra,</hi> for, and againſt the <hi>Reall Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,</hi> were exhibited by <hi>Bonner</hi> in a publick Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement; when it was no ſmall mortification (you may think) vnto that cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dged Father, to behold the faces of his vnlike children. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <note n="z" place="margin">Ouid. Met. <hi>13.</hi>
                           </note> Haud timeo, ſi jam nequeo defendere crimen,</l>
                        <l>Cum tanto commune vivo.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. But as there is no proportion in our faults (if yet I committed any) in reſpect of all the circumſtances, of <hi>Perſon, matter, manner, &amp;c.</hi> ſo ZWINGLIVS, a greater Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch then he (and one of the <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Apo.</hi> 11.3.</note> 
                     <hi>two witneſſes</hi> againſt Antichriſt, as <note n="b" place="margin">de Relig. in expoſit. <hi>4.</hi> Praecepti.</note> 
                     <hi>Zanchius</hi> belieueth) may hold out his buckler for my defence. For he (<note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Edw.</hi> phraſe. pag. <hi>100.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>mark you me now</hi>) falling away from <hi>Luther,</hi> and teaching a doctrine <hi>(of the Sacrament)</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto his former preachings, confeſſeth plainely, <q>that <note n="c" place="margin">De vera, &amp; falſa Relig.</note> he knew the truth long befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, but he ſerued the time; wherein he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by <hi>Christ</hi> as a faithfull, and wiſe ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, who <hi>giueth meate vnto his family in due ſeaſon.</hi>
                     </q> So ſayth your <hi>Zwinglius:</hi> of whom the cenſure of <note n="d" place="margin">De Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is (perhapps) very true; to witt: <hi>Zwinglius betrayeth his impiety to couer his ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> Howſoeuer it be; the cenſure of his <hi>fellow
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15355:18"/> witneſſe,</hi> 
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Loc. Com. Luth. Fabric. claſſe <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>50.</hi>
                     </note> M. LVTHER, is very terrible againſt all that <hi>Sacramentary</hi> faction; viz. <hi>He that taketh pleaſure in his owne damnation, let him belieue that the truth is taught by theis Spirits, ſince they beganne, and defend their opinions by lies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. So much for your ſecond proof; and now <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to your THIRD, which you deliuer in theis words. <note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 19.</note> 
                     <q>It is not long ſince you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned, through impatient emulation, and ambition, that, if you might haue been then preferred, and not aduiſed rather to returne to the Vniuerſity, to repayr your wings; <hi>You would not haue changed your copy ſo ſoone, nor made ſo ſorry a flight from vs to ROME.</hi> This you know to be well knowen, and, vpon farther occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may be better ſpecified vnto the world.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. I anſwere; The thought neuer entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my heart, the ſpeach neuer proceeded out of my mouth. And I am glad, as well for your owne, as my ſake, that you haue ſome other Authour, then your ſelf (who ſitt <hi>at the receipt of cuſtome,</hi> and keepe <hi>an auditt of intelligences</hi>) to <hi>ſpecify</hi> in theis behalf; that ſo, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth, and crieth <hi>adſum,</hi> I may anſwere confidently, and ſay vnto his face, <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Mentita eſt iniquitas ſibi.</hi> Wherefore, remooue theis wrongs from your ſelf vnto their proper Authours, that I may behold them in their owne center: then you are free, whoſoeuer ſhal be found guilty in this matter. For I aſſure you, that I am incredibly abuſed; and, whoſoeuer the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour be, I beſeech the Readers to vnderſtand, that <note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Inimicus homo hoc fecit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:15355:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 2.</hi> Of vnnaturall affection to my Father.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. SIR <hi>Edward</hi> is deſirous to make me o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, and contemptible in the eye of his world; and therefore he would ſhew, that I am an vnnaturall <hi>Huſband</hi> to my <hi>VVife,</hi> and, likewiſe, an vnnaturall <hi>Sonne</hi> vnto my <hi>Father;</hi> perſons, that ſhould be conjoyned with indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluble bands of loue. For the bands betwixt the firſt, are, ſacramentally, <hi>Supernaturall;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, intrinſecally <hi>Naturall,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable</hi> in both. In the firſt <hi>two are made one:</hi> in the ſecond, one brancheth from the other: ſo that, betwixt the Huſband, and Wiſe, there is a <hi>concourſe</hi> of equall duties: from the Father the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is a <hi>decourſe</hi> of affection vnto the Sonne, and, from the Sonne, a <hi>recourſe</hi> vnto the Father.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How I am condemned in the firſt reſpect, you haue <note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. §. 4.</note> already ſeene; how I am condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſecond, you ſhall now receiue a double proof. FIRST. <q>Your Father tooke a long iourney (ſaith <note n="i" place="margin">
                           <hi>pag.</hi> 17.</note> Sir <hi>Edward</hi>) to ſeek out his loſt Sonne, who neuer opened his mouth to aske him bleſsing for his paynes.</q> Then (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an amplification of no value, or ſu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtance) he addeth: <note n="k" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <q>Was not this, I ſay, grief inough, but that you muſt depriue him alſo of that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate duty, which was due vnto him?</q> And he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reupon (amongſt the reſt) he breaketh out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this paſſion; <note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 22.</note> 
                     <hi>If theis be the fruicts of your Religion, my Soule abhorreth it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15355:19"/>3. Spare my Religion, good Sir (leaſt you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the wrong; extending it vnto many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yea vnto God himſelf) and lay the faults vpon my perſon alone: ſo all Readers may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne <hi>me,</hi> as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnworthy to draw any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ayre, or to tread any longer vpon the earth. For though all are not Fathers, yet all are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; &amp; ſo, Piety in them will deteſt ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety in me.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But,<note n="m" place="margin">
                        <hi>Daniel.</hi> 13.4.</note> 
                     <hi>reuertimini ad judicium,</hi> &amp;c. Returne vnto iudgement (you impartiall Readers) and you ſhall ſee, that I will <hi>ſpecify</hi> in my owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And what <hi>ſpecification</hi> can be more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall in this caſe, then to produce thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who, onely, can be witneſſes either for Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> or againſt me, in this behalf?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Theis are my Father himſelf, and my <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>See before;</hi> §. 1 <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>num.</hi> 3.</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient friend. For my Father can not deny, that, as ſoone as I came into his vnexpected preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (which was vpon a ſonday, in the afternoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) I did immediately humble my knee, as low as my foote, and deſired his benediction, as in former times. The ſame night, and likewiſe the next morning (in the ſight, and audience of <hi>M. Etkins,</hi> at each time) I performed the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me duty, and in the ſame manner. Vpon his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, the ſame day, I intreated his bleſſing alſo, though not with the like humiliation of my body, as before, becauſe our Fare-well was taken in the open ſtreetes.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. And thus (as you ſee) at 4. ſeuerall times, in the ſpace of 24 howres, I moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately yealded that priuate duty vnto my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15355:20"/> louing Father, which Sir <hi>Edward</hi> firſt affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and then amplifieth vpon it, at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (before, to myne, now to his owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace) that <hi>I NEVER opened my mouth to do.</hi> But he, that accuſeth me herein, is the ſame man, who ſayd; <note n="n" place="margin">
                        <hi>See Chap.</hi> 1. §. 1. <hi>num.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
                     <hi>In your long prayer, at S. Dunstanes, the Reuerend.</hi> BB. <hi>(yea euen your owne Lord, &amp; Maiſter) were EVER left out for wranglers, and Antichriſtian Hierarchies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Now, if I would inſiſt in the ſtepps of your amplifying vayne, you, Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> might pardon my juſt plea againſt your injuſt wrongs; and others would ſay, that it were <hi>lex talioms;</hi> a reflexion of your owne pen, and a <note n="*" place="margin">Agens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo repati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> repaſſion from your owne action. But it was my <note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>See before; Chap.</hi> 1. §. 2. <hi>num.</hi> 17.</note> promiſe <hi>to ſpare you, though I payed others;</hi> and ſo I remitt vs both vnto them, who haue intereſt to giue their cenſure in theis things. For they, who will adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture to write, can not exempt themſelues from the juriſdiction of their Readers; but they hold out their hands for euery man to feele their pulſe, and to jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of their temper. And ſo much for your firſt; now to your SECOND proof; which is more capitall.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <q>Contrary to your Fathers expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and requeſt, and your owne ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne promiſe made vnto him, you made his preſence knowen to your CONFESSOVR: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby he might haue been in danger, <hi>as much as in you lay,</hi> to haue loſt not onely his vnnaturall Sonne, <hi>but euen his dearest life,</hi> in a ſtrange land.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. Rhetorick ſtill; but more bloudy then
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15355:20"/> before. As for my ſelf (the principall in this accuſation) I will ſay nothing: yet giue me leaue to ſpeake for others, who am thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned my ſelf. Let me then be punctuall with you, and ſearch into the probability of this danger. What was it, which my Father, &amp; my Friend did feare? Open HOSTILITY, or priuate VIOLENCE, or formall IVSTICE?</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Not open hoſtility; for there is a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> peace, a free intercourſe, and inter-traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique betwixt each contrey. And how many <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> of different quality, as well before, as ſince that time, haue conuerſed in S. <hi>Omers,</hi> more publiquely alſo, without any moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Yea I know, that ſome gaue offence, but receiued none.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Not priuate violence; for what example <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> haue you in this kind? If any, produce it: if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, why ſhould they be the firſt? And becauſe you ſeeme to lay a ſuſpition vpon the <hi>Fathers of the SOCIETY;</hi> let me aſke you firſt, whether I am, or were, in any grace with them, or no? You ſay that I am; &amp; your owne language is this: <note n="q" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>You are matriculated amongst thoſe merciles helhounds.</hi> Let me aſke you ſecondly; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you think, I had ſo little grace in me, that I would not haue interpoſed my life, and bloud, to hinder ſuch an vnchriſtian deſigne?</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Accuſe me, as you pleaſe; but let it not be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiue vnto you, that I ſhould ſpeake for others, and teſtify what I know, vpon my ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne experience; which teacheth me to <hi>speake better things.</hi> Firſt then, I ſay for that SOCIETY;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15355:21"/> that, as their ſtate of life is, ſo are their actions; religious. I am a witneſſe <hi>(for as I haue heard, ſo I haue ſeene)</hi> of the candour, and ſweetneſſe, wherewith thoſe Fathers haue intertayned their contreymen (differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from them in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as my Father is) and gaue no ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (in their words, or actions) of domeſtick ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.</note> like <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> forgeting, and forgiuing, the vnkindneſſe of his Brethren; recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the hatred, which they find at home, with loue in <hi>a ſtrange land.</hi> Which as the parties can not deny, ſo they can not but confeſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that they were not in feare of the dangers, which Sir <hi>Edward</hi> doth ſuggeſt, nor in hope of the courteſies, which themſelues did find. <hi>For which, then, of their good deeds, will he ſtone theis Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. Secondly; I can not be ſilent in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of my <hi>Confeſſour</hi> (leaſt I ſhould deny his ſingular merits) the inſtrumentall Coopera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour with God, vnto my vnſpeakeable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Why ſhould Sir <hi>Edward</hi> accuſe him, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thoughts were not embrued in this imaginary effuſion of bloud? He loued the Sonne too well to hate the Father: neither was there any cauſe for my corporall Father to be jealous of my ſpirituall Father; ſince his care was to ſaue my ſoule, but not to deſtroy his life.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Now, if open hoſtility, and priuate vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> could not be feared, was it the forme of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> which was dreadfull in their thoughts? By what ſword? <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> or <hi>Temporall?</hi> Not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15355:21"/> Eccleſiaſticall; for as there is no <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> which you can pretend; ſo the Iuriſdiction of the Biſhopp could not miniſter occaſion of their feare. For the moſt Reuerend <note n="¶" place="margin">D. IACO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BVS BLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SAEVS; <hi>natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> Flander, <hi>affectione</hi> Anglus.</note> Biſhopp of that City (<note n="ſ" place="margin">Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> Duke of Anjou. pag. <hi>106.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>of whom I am glad to make ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy mention;</hi> as well in reſpect of his owne parts; he being a ſecond, true <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great variety of learning is accompanied with eminent ſanctity of life, and an excellent grauity of perſon, tempered with gratious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fability of nature; as alſo in reſpect of his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall loue vnto our contreymen, and ſpeciall benefitts vnto many; in which number I am) the Biſhopp, I ſay, being not their Paſtour, had neither will, nor power, to proceed againſt ſuch, as offend not by publick, and notorious ſcandall; from which they did wholly decline, as knowing what appertayneth vnto honeſt, and good deportment in theis affaires. Not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Temporall; for the cauſe being not ciuill, but religious, the temporall ſword dependeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eccleſiaſticall, and is not drawen before; but after it; as <note n="t" place="margin">S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. <hi>de Conſider. lib.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith: <q>the <hi>materiall</hi> ſword, and <hi>ſpirituall</hi> ſword are both belonging vnto the Church: that is to be exerciſed <hi>for</hi> the Church, this <hi>by</hi> the Church; this by the hand of the Prieſt, that by the hand of the ſoldier; <hi>ſed ſanè ad nutum Sacerdotis, &amp; juſſum Imperatoris.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15. If then they were (as, indeed, they were) free from danger in, or by any of theis meanes, either <note n="u" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.6.</note> 
                     <hi>they feared, where no feare was,</hi> or, by this pretenſe of feare, they would deriue hatred v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thoſe men, who were deſirous to giue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15355:22"/> them the pledges of their loue. And this is no new deuiſe in our contreymen (of Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> Religion) <hi>to ſpeak euill for good</hi> (vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their returne out of <hi>Catholick</hi> lands) to procure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt hatred by vnneceſſary feare: as <note n="❀" place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 13 33.</note> ſome vngratefull viſitours of <hi>Canaan, did speake euill of it,</hi> and gaue out reports of the <hi>terrible Giants</hi> therein, purpoſely to deterr the people from making entrance into <hi>the land of promiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 3.</hi> Violation of promiſes, and Oaths.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. I Am now arriued vpon the laſt accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which toucheth my <hi>infidelity,</hi> and <hi>perjury.</hi> An example of the firſt, was me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned <note n="*" place="margin">§. 2. <hi>num.</hi> 8.</note> befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and is to be conſidered heere; viz. <hi>Contrary to your ſolemne promiſe, you made your Fathers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence knowen to your Confeſſour.</hi> Which accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may appeare vntrue; becauſe the Letter (whereof ſomething is <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. §. 2. <hi>num.</hi> 11.</note> already ſpoken) though it hath not fauoured me in any relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet it is wholly ſilent in this point. For thus ſaith the Authour thereof, in my Fathers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. <hi>Being in S. Omers, I willed, and chardged him</hi> (my Sonne) <hi>not to reueale my being there: not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he made it knowen the ſame night; as, vpon examination, he confeſſed vnto me the next morning: which made vs preſently to come away, fearing our liues to be in danger amongſt ſuch a company of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, as that towne is stuffed withall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Behold (on my Fathers part) <hi>willing,</hi> and <hi>chardging</hi> me not to reueale his preſence: but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15355:22"/> (on my part) no <hi>promiſe;</hi> either ſimple, or <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne.</hi> Which point being of ſingular aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge againſt me, if it had been true, had not been concealed in that Letter, wherein each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular hath the waight of all circumſtances (more then due alſo) to aggrauate the quality of my offence. But as my memory doth not witneſſe, nor my conſcience accuſe me of any ſuch ſolemne promiſe, ſo it imported me, for juſt cauſes, to retayn my liberty therein.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For when my Father, and my Friend (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe true name, and quality were knowen, vpon ſome accident, before I ſaw him) preſſed me very earneſtly to returne; I deſired, of them, a time of deliberation, for my mature, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn anſwere.<note n="x" place="margin">Cic.</note> 
                     <hi>Diu deliberandum, quod ſtatuendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſemel.</hi> I was to conſider <hi>long</hi> vpon that, which I was, but <hi>once,</hi> to vndertake; my caſe being like vnto his, who hath the conduct of an army, &amp; can make but <hi>one</hi> fault in warr (as <note n="y" place="margin">
                        <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in apo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Reg. &amp; <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Scipio</hi> ſaid; <hi>A man can not make two faults in warr</hi>) becauſe there is no remedy, but ruine by the firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can committ the ſecond. So it was in my affaire; I was to ſtand, or fall, in body, and ſoule, vpon this accepta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; preſent choyce.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whereupon, finding my ſelf mooued in conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to take aduiſe with, and from, him, whoſe counſayle was vnto me, as <hi>the oracle of God,</hi> in all ſpirituall things; I acquainted my Father, expreſſly, with my reſolution herein; ſhewing him alſo, that, by detection of his preſence, no danger ſhould, or could enſue. And though he was very willing to diuert me
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15355:23"/> from this courſe, yet, ſeeing my conſtancy, he made me an abſolute (I might ſay <hi>ſolemne</hi>) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, not to depart from <hi>S. Omers,</hi> before the tueſday morning; ſo that I ſhould haue the whole monday for time of deliberation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my requeſt. So ſtill, here was no promiſe from me, not to reueale his preſence; but rather the contrary: and this may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vnto the objection of the Knight.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Now, whatſoeuer my Fathers comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, or chardge was, or howſoeuer he may think, that I erred in obedience, or others, that I fayled in diſcretion; yet my conſcience did thus ſolicite me, with hir effectuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But whereas it is ſayd farther, that <hi>I, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon examination the next morning, confeſſed, how I had reuealed his preſence, the laſt light, vnto a Popiſh Priest, and that THIS made him come away, fearing,</hi> &amp;c. I muſt humbly intreate pardon to ſhew, that my <hi>confeſsion</hi> was not the cauſe of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayn departure.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. For when I tooke leaue of him, and of my friend, vpon the Sonday night, I left them in their reſolution (as it ſeemed vnto me) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect my anſwere (for returne) vpon monday in the euening, or (rather) vpon tueſday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and, accordingly, I intended to prepare my anſwere, either <hi>yea,</hi> or <hi>no,</hi> as the difficulties ſhould preſent themſelues vnto me, vpon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re exact recollection of my thoughts. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, comming vnto his chamber, on the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day morning, I found him prouiding to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, with as much ſpeed, as he could. Wherefore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15355:23"/> my ſayd confeſsion (that <hi>I had reuealed his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence vnto a Popiſh Priest</hi>) was not occaſion of that departure, which he had prepared, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued vpon, before I entered into his ſight. And though this were no leſſe grieuous vnto me, then vnexpected, yet he gaue me no ſuch reaſon of this departure; but, that <hi>his money fell ſhort; things were vncertayn;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Thus much of my <hi>Infidelity;</hi> now I am to treate of <hi>Perjury:</hi> whereof three remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are produced by the Knight. FIRST. <note n="z" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 17.</note> 
                     <hi>You did proteſt, as you hoped to haue any part in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious paſsion, that, within three weeks, at the fartheſt (if you liued ſo long) you would be in England, after your Fathers returne; &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <hi>You made your Father a ſorrowfull witneſſe of your perjurious vow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. I will not deny any thing, <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</note> 
                     <hi>whereunto my Knowledge can ſuſcribe.</hi> It is true therefore; I promiſed to returne. But you muſt obſerue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> with me FIRST, the inference of this point, and the connexion, which it hath with the premiſes. viz. <hi>You wrote a little Pamphlet contrary vnto the principles of the Romiſh profeſsion.</hi> When? <hi>After your reconciliation vnto that Synagogue.</hi> What doth that prooue? <hi>Your ſmall liking vnto that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And</hi> (ſayth the Knight, immediately therevpon) <hi>were you not now in Huckſters hands, whoſe vigilant eyes haue mewed you vp in their idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous cage, I dare ſay you had been in England long ſi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ce;</hi> FOR <hi>ſo you did proteſt,</hi> &amp;c. Behold then the inference, heere, is to ſhew my procliuity to renounce the <hi>Catholick Romane</hi> faith, as a thing not intertayned in the ſecrete approbation of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15355:24"/> my heart. But of this ſcandalous imputation I haue already treated in the <note n="*" place="margin">§. 1. <hi>num.</hi> 6 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> precedents; vnto which I muſt now remitt the courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. SECONDLY; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the manner of this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (viz. <hi>as I hoped to haue any part,</hi> &amp;c.) I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can remember, nor will acknowledge to haue proceeded from my lippes. That, which my memory, and conſcience can beſt teſtify vnto me, is, that I ſayd; <hi>by the grace of God.</hi> Which is a ſpeach of great importance, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe; but yet (formally) it hath not ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in exaggeration, as the other.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. THIRDLY; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> becauſe Sir <hi>Edward</hi> doth dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſo preciſely with me, I may not giue him leaue thus to circumciſe the time, nor to chandge my words, at his owne pleaſure. For I ſayd not abſolutely, WITHIN THREE WEEKES, <hi>at the fartheſt, I will returne;</hi> but I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a <hi>forſan</hi> (with which particle Sir <hi>Edward</hi> helpeth himſelf <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 47.</note> elſewhere, to triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph ouer me, yet without a victory) PERHAPPS <hi>within three, or four weeks: I cannot certainly reſolue vpon the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</hi> And ſo, I know no reaſon, why, vpon my returne within this yeare, or more, my word might not ſtand inuiolate, and entire, in that reſpect, if I would rather preſſe Sir <hi>Edward</hi> with outward reaſons, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acquaint him with my inward thoughts.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. To come then more particularly vnto matter it ſelf; as I deny not my ſpeach, and, therewith, my intention, that, <hi>by the grace of God, I would returne,</hi> &amp;c. ſo there are many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15355:24"/> heerein, and ſpecially three, which may eaſe the burthen, and cleare the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, on my behalf.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. FIRST; that my Father, and friend, knew my reſolution to be vnprepared; and yet now they would force it vnto a birth, before the prefixed time. For it was my HOPE, and it was their PROMISE, that I ſhould haue the whole Monday for my deliberation; which was now denied. Wherefore this their ſodayn (and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary) departure (contrary vnto both) was the firſt cauſe of my abortiue promiſe; borne, before it was conceiued.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. SECONDLY; my ſympathizing eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the ſtreame of teares, flowing from a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe fountayn of <hi>loue,</hi> and <hi>grief,</hi> in my deare, and carefull Father: which was the ſtrongeſt elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of Nature to perſwade my vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded ſelf; who (being <note n="*" place="margin">S. Auguſt. <hi>Conf. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> 
                     <hi>filius tantarum lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum</hi>) knew not what to ſay, or think, when my Soule ſuffred a diſſipatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all hir powers. Mettall ſo ſoftened was fitt for any impreſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It was not a <hi>returne,</hi> into a CONTREY, with a FATHER (things of no ſmall value, in all mens eſtimation) but the preſent expenſe of my <hi>dearest life,</hi> which I could, and ſhould haue promiſed to ſatisfy ſuch loue, and to mollify ſuch grief. <hi>Si haec tempeſtas propterme orta eſt,</hi> &amp;c. if all this be for my ſake, diſpoſe of me, at your owne will.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. THIRDLY; though I was thus preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them, beſides my expectation, and ſo caried out of my ſelf, beyond my ſtrength; yet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15355:25"/> there was annexed vnto my promiſe of <hi>returne,</hi> a condition of <hi>ſecurity.</hi> But where ſhould I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiue it? At <hi>Douer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15. Behold now my errour, which drew on my fault. For hauing thus incautelouſly, and improuidently (in my benummed ſpirits) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de my promiſe to returne, <hi>ſo that I might receiue ſecurity at Douer;</hi> and perceiuing, afterward, what danger I might incurre (though I doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not of my friends good will, but of their power onely) I deſired, that my ſecurity might giue me meeting at <hi>Calais:</hi> leaſt, otherwiſe, the Land might prooue more da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous then Sea; and ſpecially for two reaſons. The ONE; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I then had (as now I haue) a grounded reſolution of heart, to remayn a conſtant me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Catholick, Romane</hi> Church (<hi>from which the certainty of faith is to be ſought,</hi> ſaith <note n="d" place="margin">Part. <hi>1.</hi> Serm. coram Alexand. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Gerſon;</hi> a <note n="e" place="margin">D. Field. pag. <hi>85.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>worthy guide of Gods Church</hi>) &amp; the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore I ſhould be leſſe acceptable vnto them, whom, in all temporall things, I would gladly reuerence, and obay. The OTHER; becauſe I ſtood the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charged vpon the point of <hi>Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,</hi> which <hi>M. Etkins</hi> did inſinuate vnto me at <hi>S. Omers,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward</hi> hath now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in his Letter, to prejudice the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of my <note n="*" place="margin">§. 1. <hi>num.</hi> 6.7.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Faith,</hi> and ſafety of my <hi>Life.</hi> But as he doth vntruly accuſe me of <hi>Reconciliation</hi> in ENGLAND, ſo my ignorance of the Law ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de me too <hi>confident,</hi> and too <hi>fearrefull</hi> alſo; in this reſpect. Too <hi>confident;</hi> for when I knew, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally, that <hi>Reconciliation</hi> is onely a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall act, to reduce vs into the fauour of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15355:25"/> God, and vnity of his Church, I did not ſuſpect the ſeuerity of the Law therein; &amp; therefore, out of the comfort, and exultation of mine owne heart, I imparted ſomething, in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, by my Letters vnto a perſon of eminent dignity, and place. Too <hi>fearfull:</hi> for vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (afterward) the penalty of <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> and not knowing how farr the ſtatute exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in this caſe, I thought the perill to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, whether within his Majeſties domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or without the ſame; neither had I any notice to the contrary, till I peruſed the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes; not many howres, before the writing hereof.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Now, if my Father, and my Friend, did feare the loſſe of their <hi>dearest liues,</hi> where no law was in force againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor any man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a thought prejudiciall vnto the leaſt droppe of their bloud, and yet did <hi>therefore</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from S. <hi>Omers,</hi> againſt their owne promiſe, and without any cauſe; had not I juſt reaſon to prouide ſecurely for my ſelf, when my life ſhould be <note n="*" place="margin">As I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd.</note> actually in the mercy of juſtice, &amp; expoſed vnto continuall danger, vpon ſome ineuitable acts of my Religion?</p>
                  <p n="17">17. Thus you (ſee <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ood Readers) wherein I fayle, as alſo vpon what <hi>precedent,</hi> and <hi>conſequent</hi> reaſons. If, heeretofore, you haue wholly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned me, I appeale from your firſt, vnto your ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and better thoughts. If, now, you excuſe me wholly, you do more for me, then I would do for my ſelf. For as I find ſome thing, which I may defend, and ſome thing,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15355:26"/> which I may excuſe, ſo there is ſome thing, which I may, and do condemne. And ſo I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend my ſelf, with this matter, vnto the mercy of God, and vnto the charity of the Readers; deſiring them to make this caſe their owne, before they giue their ſentence vpon me.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. The SECOND remonſtrance of my perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Sir <hi>Edward</hi> deliuereth in this ſort. <note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <hi>The like ſolemne oath you tooke in the preſence of M. Etkins, that, vpon the faith of a Romane Catholick, and as you hoped to be ſaued, this booke of yours, which you then ſhewed him, ſhould not be printed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="19">19. A <hi>ſolemne promiſe</hi> before; and now <hi>a ſolemne oath;</hi> in both which your dealing is not ſimple, but double. Leauing therefore the formes of theis proteſtations, as calumniating exaggera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (for, euermore, there is <note n="❀" place="margin">4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.40.</note> 
                     <hi>Mors in olla;</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me euill herb in your beſt pottage) I anſwere, that it was my promiſe, and reſolution to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe that booke. But how? Reſpectiuely, vpon the opinion, and hope of my returne; which comming not to paſſe, according to my juſt, and neceſſary deſire, I was, and am (in conſcience, and in reaſon) acquitted from that promiſe. Heere alſo you muſt obſerue, that <hi>M. Etkins</hi> was at S. <hi>Omers</hi> in <hi>May,</hi> and that this Booke was ſuppreſſed vntill <note n="†" place="margin">It was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt commited to the preſſe.</note> 
                     <hi>October</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing: whereby you may perceiue, that, till I was in deſpayr of returne, I gaue it not leaue to iſſue forth into the publick view.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Farther; I was yet prouoked hereunto by many, and groſſe indignities; of ſome my
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15355:26"/> 
                     <hi>Betters,</hi> whom I alwayes honoured; of ſome my <hi>Equalls,</hi> whom I alwayes loued; of ſome my <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours,</hi> whom I neuer offended; of many <hi>stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> whom I had wronged, no more then Sir <hi>Edward</hi> himſelf; and this, he will confeſſe, was in a very meane degree.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Finally; charity vnto <hi>my ſelf,</hi> to vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te my name from reproach; charity vnto <hi>others,</hi> to draw them out of the ſnare of death; and (aboue all) my gratitude vnto my <hi>Lord</hi> for his great mercy, did vrdge, inforce, and impell me vnto that courſe.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. I come now vnto the THIRD, and laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of my perjury; viz. <note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Your Wife, and Creditours are throughly acquainted with many ſuch your voluntary, and intended perjuries; as, vpon your next reply, ſhall be more particularly ſpecified: vnder whoſe name ſo euer you meane to couer it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="23">23. You ſee that I come vnmaſked into your preſence; I borrow not the face of any man to couer my ſhame: <hi>Specify</hi> therefore, if you plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; and, if it be an act of Cheualry to be an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex</hi>-maker of other mens liues, ſpare me not: <hi>Vtere tuo judicio; nihil enim impedio.</hi> But yet, <note n="*" place="margin">Tere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And. Act. <hi>1.</hi> Sc. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ne temerè facias, ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tu haud dicas tibi non praedictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, CAVE.</hi> Let diſcretion be the vſher of your action, and temember, that <hi>TAKE HEED is a fayr warning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="24">24. Now to your accuſation. It may ſeeme ſtrange, that neither your Charity preuayled with you, nor Philoſophy taught you, to dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le more ſparingly with my <hi>Intention;</hi> which being not a tranſient, but an immanent act (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15355:27"/> in the will) is knowen (certainly) vnto none, but vnto God alone; by whom alſo it may be communicated vnto others, by reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or repreſented by viſion, according to his pleaſure.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. But it is a more vnchriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and vnknightly part to make my WIFE a <hi>witneſſe</hi> againſt me (&amp; ſpecially, without any iuſt cauſe) which the Lawes themſelues permitt not, or exact not, in caſes of greater importance. Howbeit, my charity toward hir will make me vncharitable toward you. Wherefore, Sir, I belieue you not. Your wrongs againſt me teach me, that you may wrong hir; ſo that, accepting your teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in this caſe, I ſhould make a forfaiture of my reaſon.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. As for my <hi>Creditours;</hi> I confeſſe vnto you, that, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> probability, or hope, or (ſuppoſed) certainty of receiuing moneyes, I haue been ſometimes deceiued, and they, conſequently, by me. I confeſſe vnto you farther, that, neere vpon my departure, I was more liberall in my promiſe vnto one man, then I ſhould haue been. And thus Sir <hi>Edward</hi> alſo is now beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me my CONFESSOVR; who (I doubt not) for my plaineneſſe, and ſyncerity, will giue me a ſpeedy abſolution, and a gentle pennance.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. Heere (courteous Readers) the Scene of <hi>criminall</hi> accuſations is done. Wherefore I will take the <hi>Actour</hi> aſide (his part being ended) and, in a friendly manner, I will addreſſe my ſelf to intertayn him with a new diſcourſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:15355:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>§. 4.</hi> A kind expoſtulation with Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> vpon the former wrongs; and a charitable inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation thereof.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. SIR EDWARD; there are three things, which I eſteeme very deare, &amp; pretious: the ſafety of my <hi>Life;</hi> the honeſty of my <hi>Name;</hi> the ſaluation of my <hi>Soule.</hi> The firſt may be, the ſecond is, the third neither is, nor may be, in your power. The firſt I will ſubmitt vnto the benignity of my <hi>Souereigne,</hi> to giue, or take it: the third ſtandeth at the mercy of my <hi>Lord,</hi> to ſaue, or deſtroy it: the ſecond remayneth at the charity of <hi>others,</hi> to ſuffer wrong, or to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn right. For as in this particular (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning my <hi>Name</hi>) you are actiue, and I paſſiue; ſo the Reader is vncertayn vnto vs both, either to pronounce me guilty, or you injurious.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But I haue vnfolded, and he may now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, your SIFTING Paragraph; vnto which if I ſhould giue the due aſpiration (<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudic.</hi> 12.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Shibboleth</hi> for <hi>Sibboleth</hi>) you might, and he would, pardon my juſt boldneſſe therein.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For FIRST; my Innocency, in the <hi>things</hi> themſelues, pleadeth effectually for my defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and your reproof. SECONDLY; my Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy alſo toward your owne <hi>perſon;</hi> which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by hand, mouth, or heart; in deed, word, or thought. THIRDLY; our vnequall <hi>quality</hi> ſaith, that a noble <hi>Knight</hi> ſhould not thus intreate a poore <hi>Scholler;</hi> ſince you ſhould be as farr from doing me a wrong with a <hi>Pen,</hi> as I am vnable, or vnfitt, to anſwere it with a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15355:28"/> 
                     <hi>Sword.</hi> For, howſoeuer you ſpeake of your <note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>lin.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>often employments with both,</hi> yet I (and I know not your mind alſo) would rather chooſe, with <note n="i" place="margin">Plutarch. in <hi>Eumen.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Eumenes,</hi> to beare <hi>pen, and paper,</hi> then, with <hi>Neoptolemus,</hi> a <hi>ſword, &amp; targett.</hi> FOVRTH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY; the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, by which your matter is caried, proclaymeth, that you were more willing to diſgrace my name, then able to reſolue my doubts.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I ſayd, and I ſhewed, that <hi>the euidence of Scripture, the rule of Apoſtolicall Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the practiſe of the ancient, and VNIVERSALL Church, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Fathers, the vntruths of ſome chief Protestants,</hi> did ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly induce, and perſwade me, firſt to a juſt ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a neceſſary rejectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my late <hi>Proteſtanticall</hi> faith. And leaſt the Anſwerer of my diſcourſe ſhould <note n="*" place="margin">Firſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. <hi>pag.</hi> 94.</note>
                     <hi>throw duſt into the ayre, with more contention, then profitt</hi> (as you haue done) I preuented ſuch exorbitant courſes, and preſcribed the due, true, and abſolute me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, which he muſt obſerue; viz. <hi>to oppoſe, and to prooue, a CONTRARY aſſertion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to each particular in my diſcourſe:</hi> as, that <hi>Prayer for the dead deſcended not from the Apostles:</hi> that <hi>the Vniuerſall Church (in S. Auguſtines time, euen by his owne testimony) did not referr Prayer for the dead vnto the SOVLES; and to the ſoules, remayning in a temporall payn.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Theis things you ſhould haue fairely, and orderly refuted; taking the particulars in their place, and courſe, as they were plainely, and methodically repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto you in my MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVE. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there had bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charity in your pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15355:28"/> and judgement in your fact. But you (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a digreſſion in your very ingreſſe) <hi>ſift the cauſes of my Alienation</hi> (not ſuch as I deliuer, but ſuch as you deuiſe) and runne, vaſtly, into my <hi>Puritamſme,</hi> my <hi>perjury,</hi> my <hi>vnnaturall affection,</hi> my <hi>diſconceipt toward the Romane faith,</hi> &amp;c. that ſo, vndermining my creditt, with your engins, at the firſt, you might, afterward, blow me vp with more facility, and eaſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Now, for my owne comportment, and behauiour in making my anſwere vnto this <hi>ſifting Paragraph;</hi> though the Reader (I preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me) hath (or might) obſerue it, without any farther remonſtrance, or declaration from me; yet I will briefly, and plainely bring it vnto his conſideration, in this place.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. FIRST then he might obſerue me to be free from the <hi>commiſsion</hi> of many, and from the <hi>concealement</hi> of other faults. In the firſt reſpect; a <hi>knowen</hi> wrong is a ſufficient remedy for it ſelf. In the ſecond; my ſorrow may be a ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. <note n="k" place="margin">Senecae.</note> 
                     <hi>Quem poenitet peccâſſe, penè eſt innnocens.</hi> Let my <hi>Repentance,</hi> therefore, for that, which I haue done amiſſe, make it vndone, in your charitable thoughts. God himſelf accepteth this Sacrifice yea his <hi>Mercy</hi> bindeth the eyes of his Diuinity, hiding that from himſelf, which euery man ſeeth, &amp; making him forgett that, which he knew, before it was committed. Heere is the <hi>prototypus,</hi> by which our acts, and judgements muſt be drawen; that ſo we may make our ſelues like vnto him in our actions, who made vs like himſelf in our creation.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15355:29"/>8. SECONDLY; he might obſerue my <hi>Patience,</hi> which ſheweth it ſelf in the perpetuall courſe of my ſtyle. <hi>We are reuiled, and we reuile not agayn.</hi> Heerein I had rather haue a victory ouer my ſelf, to conquere my paſsions, then ouer you to requite your wrongs. Beſides; I haue had a remembrance, and reſpect of your bloud, as being a <note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 50.</note> 
                     <hi>Gentleman;</hi> of your quality, as being a <hi>Knight;</hi> of your fauour, and grace with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as being his <note n="m" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 105.</note> 
                     <hi>Seruant;</hi> of your conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity, and affinity, as being allyed vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of <hi>higheſt rank;</hi> finally, of your <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 49.</note> affection vnto that <note n="❀" place="margin">Oxford.</note> 
                     <hi>Vniuerſity,</hi> which I am bound to reuerence, and of your inueſtiture therein with a <note n="n" place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Degree,</hi> by which you are honoured, and which is honoured by you.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Thus I haue ſubdued my paſsions vnto the ſtrength of reaſon, and humbled my reaſon vnto the power of grace; that, as the Rock ſtandeth vnmooueable in the raging, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious waues, ſo I might be quiet, modeſt, &amp; temperate in the middeſt of theis great wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs; ſo great (perhapps) as can admitt no parallele in theis later yeares, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like reſpects.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. And thus, as the beneuolous Reader hath ſeene my cariadge to be no wayes correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vnto the wrongs, ſo farther, he ſhall now ſee my CHARITY alſo; which will eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that, ſince <hi>Malice,</hi> and <hi>Falſehood,</hi> are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vices (and ſpecially in men of his eminent place) Sir <hi>Edward</hi> may, and will decline theis imputations, by ſome probable, and conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t excuſe.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <pb facs="tcp:15355:29"/>11. FIRST then, it may be, that ſecrete loue to recall me, and not open malice to defame me, inuited him vnto this courſe; as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <note n="o" place="margin">
                        <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 44.</note> 
                     <hi>Benjamin</hi> was accuſed of ſecrete theft, by the policy of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> his kind, and vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brother. And this I do the rather conceiue, becauſe my <note n="❀" place="margin">In the afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſayd Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> Father himſelf ſeemeth to be <hi>in hope, that the whole rabble of Papists ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand ſo much (by Sir Edward Hoby) of the cauſe of my comming to their hotch-potch Religion, that they will be aſhamed to patronize me any longer, if they be not paſt all ſhame.</hi> The meaning whereof is, either that I ſhould want my part in the <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Terram de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit homimbꝰ.</hi> Pſal. 113.16</note> common portion of mankind (which I can not ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe) or that, being deſtitute of relief in all <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> lands, I might returne home agayn, as the <note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.</note> loſt Sonne, vnto his louing Father.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. SECONDLY; it may be, that, in purſuing, &amp; hunting me, he followed the ſent of informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and drew my picture conformably vnto that <hi>Idea,</hi> which other mens <hi>report,</hi> and not his owne <hi>fiction,</hi> had formerly imprinted in his mind. So <hi>Pythia</hi> gaue hir anſwere, as ſhe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it from <hi>Apollo;</hi> and <hi>Tireſias</hi> prophecied v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the flight of birds, according to the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Manto.</hi> In this caſe, the thing may be <hi>falſe,</hi> but the perſon doth not <note n="❀" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mentiri</hi> eſt contra me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ire. S. Aug.</note> 
                     <hi>lye,</hi> whoſe words are anſwerable vnto his thoughts.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. If it be ſo with you, Sir <hi>Edward</hi> (and I wiſh it ſo, for your owne honour) you are wronged the more, but I nothing the leſſe. Wherefore (by alluſion, not compariſon) I may iuſtly ſay;<note n="q" place="margin">
                        <hi>Io.</hi> 19.11.</note> 
                     <hi>He, that deliuered me vnto you, hath the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15355:30"/> greater ſinne.</hi> A ſinne toward me, by abuſing my name; a ſinne toward you, by abuſing your pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Such a victory, therefore, as you haue gotten herein, if it were my ſhame, yet it is alſo your owne grief. <hi>Victus occubuit, &amp; victor fleuit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14. But yet I liue; that is the mercy of my Lord: I want not conuenient meanes; that is the kindneſſe of my friends: I remayn in their good opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not impayred, but increaſed; that is againſt a ſubtile (perhapps malitious) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. My conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is free; wherein I triumph: my name is cleared; wherein I rejoyce.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. <note n="r" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.17.</note> 
                     <hi>From henceforth,</hi> then, <hi>let no man be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vnto me,</hi> nor vnto himſelf. This is my firſt, and it ſhall be my laſt (the <hi>non vltra</hi>) of my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in this kind. For ſince my Aduerſaries haue fayled in the beginning (the <hi>firſt borne,</hi> &amp; <hi>strength</hi>) of their aſſaults, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I looke for greater exactneſſe in their rechardge, &amp; in their ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d attempt? No; <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                        <hi>Io.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Omnis homo primùm bonum vinum ponit, et, cùm inebriati fuerint, tunc id, quod deterius est:</hi> the beſt is drawen at the firſt; that, which enſueth, is leſſe ſyncere, and pure. Farther; ſince a KNIGHT hath fayled in his enterpriſe, can I expect more fidelity from others, whoſe quality hath not ſuch a ſpeciall obligation of HONOVR, to require it at their hands? No; <hi>Schollers,</hi> who profeſſe the <hi>pen,</hi> may be more profound in knowledge, but <hi>Knights,</hi> who profeſſe the <hi>ſword,</hi> are more punctuall in their credit.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Finally therefore; let my Aduerſaries throw out their calumnious ſcripts, as the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15355:30"/> haile, yet no indignity ſhall trouble my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed thoughts; but, <note n="t" place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc</hi> 21.19.</note> 
                     <hi>poſſeſſing my ſoule in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> I will anſwere the Authours with ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, their workes with contempt.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of the FIRST PART.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:15355:31"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Readers.</head>
            <p>BEENEVOLOVS READERS; perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture you haue meruayled very much, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Why my Anſwere vnto Sir</hi> EDWARD HOBYES <hi>Letter, hath been ſo long in comming?</hi> and will mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> more, <hi>Why, being now come, it is ſo ſhort?</hi> Vnto both theis demands, I will giue you a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; brief, and true.</p>
            <p>Concerning the FIRST then; you muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that, whereas Sir <hi>Edwards</hi> Letter was publiſhed in <hi>Iune</hi> laſt, and had <note n="❀" place="margin">In his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. to the <hi>Ladies.</hi>
               </note> direction, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, to ſalute me at S. <hi>Omers;</hi> I departed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in <hi>May</hi> before, and trauayled into <hi>France:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re I had the firſt notice of this Letter, about the middeſt of <hi>Iuly</hi> following, but had no ſight thereof till about the end of that moneth; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually alſo, as it paſſed, by me in <hi>Roan,</hi> vnto a Doctour in <hi>Paris:</hi> ſo that I could not then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn it, aboue 8. howres, in my hands. And though I gaue preſent order vnto a Poſt, to bring me a copie from <hi>London,</hi> yet he fayled me; and ſo I was conſtrayned (vpon his retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) to borrow the former copie; which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in <hi>September;</hi> but, for ſome impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, it lay by me, vntill <hi>October;</hi> when (according to the ſmall portion of time, which I could allot vnto ſuch affayres) I beganne to addreſſe my anſwere.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15355:31"/>
            <p>Whereby, as the Reader may perceiue the cauſes of this delay, ſo Sir <hi>Edward</hi> himſelf may ſee the little courteſy of the LADIES to him, in recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his great <note n="†" place="margin">In his ſayd <hi>Letter</hi> vnto them.</note> kindneſſe to them; who would not vouchſafe him the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or (to vſe his owne word) yeald him ſo much <hi>boone,</hi> as to procure <hi>the deliuery of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed</hi> Letter vnto me, at S. <hi>Omers;</hi> whither (as farr, as I can learne) it was neuer convaighed by their meanes.</p>
            <p>Concerning the SECOND; it may pleaſe you to vnderſtand farther, that, as I prouided my anſwere vnto the whole Letter (digeſted, by the Authout, into SIX PARAGRAPHS; as you haue already ſeene in my <hi>Preface</hi>) and had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed a very ſmall parcell thereof, I was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by a Catholick Gentleman (comming lately, out of <hi>England,</hi> into theis parts) that my ANSWERE vnto Sir <hi>Edward Hoby</hi> (and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the <hi>morall points,</hi> in his <hi>ſifting Paragraph</hi>) was earneſtly expected, both by my friends, &amp; aduerſaries; amongſt whom, Maiſter L. D. (a Miniſter, and ſometimes kindly affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me) beſtowing his liberality vpon M. <hi>Humfrey Leech,</hi> and me, pretended, that I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther durſt, nor could anſwere the KNIGHT; and, that my long ſilence was a ſufficient proof.</p>
            <p>For this reſpect then, I am inforced to ſend away this <hi>Firſt Part</hi> of my <hi>Apology</hi> with ſpeed, and to make it the harbenger of the reſt. A ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reaſon alſo of this ſingle, and haſty birth, is, in regard of the news (truly, and juſtly grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15355:32"/> vnto my heart) which was brought vnto me, by the ſayd Cath. Gentleman, concerning my late, honourable Lord, the L. Biſhopp of <hi>London,</hi> lying ſick, &amp; in emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perill of death. Wherefore, hauing <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.12.</note> appealed vnto his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp, as being a moſt competent witneſſe for my defence, I deſired, that (if it were poſsible) this poore ſchedule might be preſented vnto his view, before his paſſadge out of this world. And, if my heartieſt prayers could preuayle any thing with him, who hath ſouereigne power ouer vs all, for <hi>Life,</hi> &amp; <hi>Death,</hi> for <hi>Body,</hi> and <hi>Soule,</hi> he knoweth, that <hi>clamaui de profundis</hi> &amp;c. I haue called, and I haue cried vnto him, out of the depth of my ſoule, for my ſayd louing Maiſter; either to grant him a longer life heere, or an happier elſwhere. His affection toward me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued this requitall from me; as you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by his owne words; viz. <hi>I wiſh M. Hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons better, then any man in England; I except not his owne Father,</hi> &amp;c. which he <note n="†" place="margin">Fulham <hi>houſe.</hi> 9. <hi>August.</hi> 1609.</note> wrote vnto a very honorable Gentleman; <hi>avowing</hi> vnto him far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>vpon his credit,</hi> that <hi>he neither knew, nor heard of Sir Edward Hobies booke, till he ſaw it in print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue (good Readers) a ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto each demand. It may pleaſe you now fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to vnderſtand, that the reſidue of my <hi>Apology</hi> (wherein, I am ſory that the Knight doth prouoke me to incounter his <hi>weake, vntrue,</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous</hi> exceptions) ſhall come foorth, in due time, accompanied with a <hi>Reply</hi> vnto D. <hi>Mortons Anſwere;</hi> which he calleth a <hi>direct</hi> one; but he ſhall ſee it <hi>corrected,</hi> to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitt,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15355:32"/> if he will, or to his loſſe, though he would not. If the delay ſhall prooue more te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, then will conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you, and the diſcourſe more rude, then will becomme me; you muſt remember, that, as my <hi>Trauaile</hi> was, and is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for other vſes, then to write, ſo it doth not affoord either leyſure, or meanes, which are requiſite in this behalf.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare you well.</salute> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Roan.</hi> 
                  <date>Decemb. 24. 1609.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Dilige Deum, amicos in Deo, inimicos propter Deum.</p> 
                  <bibl>S. AVGVST.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:15355:33"/>
            <head>Errours paſſed in ſome copies.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>lin.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Fault.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Correction.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>clamours</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>clamorous</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>great) in</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>great (in</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>30.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ambigous</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ambiguous</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>porportion</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>proportion</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pen,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>pen)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>the cenſure of Bell.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Bellarmines ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſure</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>32.</cell>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>forgeting</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>forgetting</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>then ſea</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>then the Sea</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="4">
                        <hi>In the Margent.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="3">16. <hi>Galath.</hi> 5.9.</cell>
                     <cell>Galath. 5.15.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
